World War II letters, 1941-1946
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Series 6: Letters from Henry Rube
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 16, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Located in Louisiana • Tells his dad that it would be better for Willie to be drafted instead of work on the ranch. That the army will straighten him up where if he works on the ranch he will get worse each time • Says that Willie needs to learn the hard way & the Army will teach him. Henry offered to talk to him as well.
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 23, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Said that their clothes do not last where they are at and is asking for them to send him two more coveralls—Army type • Sent a specific order to the man that owns the store where they sell coveralls
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 3, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Connie and John went home at the same time • He was in the swamps & will be there for a few weeks
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (August 18, 1943; Location—Camp Polk, Louisiana) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Talk about how Dave is picking grapes • Make fun of each other and how their spelling is
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 1, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Promotion came & now he’s a First Lieutenant (silver bars) • He has been very busy & hasn’t slept in 10 days
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 23, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Asks how the raisins comings along • Tries to think positive—“If it isn’t fine, we’ll make it that way. That is the only way to get along in the Army."
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 12, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Asks for John’s address
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 24, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Says that is another Christmas without them • Says that it’s the first time that he’s working on Christmas day • Will be sending a footlocker and sleeping bad because he won’t need it there • He has the job as the company commander while the company commander gets better for as he became ill
  - Letter to Dad from Henry (December 28, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Asks his Dad to do three things: send him his [Henry's] will that is in his deposit box—wants to check it for changes • Contact Bank of America ("little bank") where he has his savings account and create a checking account on his behalf, but to make sure that his Dad can draw or deposit when necessary • Send Henry the bank branch number and street so the government will know the address of the bank for the allotment • Doesn’t want to carry a lot of money, and it’s better for the bank to send the money directly to the bank
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (January 15, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Weather—snowed • Two packages going home with personal papers to save because a lot of them are his records of being in the army • Gives some of his clothes to his family • Sent Kay $25 for Christmas [money is not in envelope] • Said to use any of his money—for church put his part, for insurance, anything
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (March 27, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Emma [sister] sent him a snapshot of herself – she’s growing up [photo is not in envelope]
  - Letter to Family from Henry (April 16, 1944, Location—New Guinea) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Uneventful week, working as usual • Letters are taking long to arrive • Letters the family writes is not censored at all, the only ones that are censored are the ones being sent out from the soldiers • They have been spending their recreation time playing volleyball games against the officers and boxing • Told Dave to send him film
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (April 30, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Learned about Morse Code • Radio plays a lot of good music • Goes to church about three times a week • They make their own fun—will be practicing with Morse Code again
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (May 7, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Says that John wrote him thinks they are near each other, but he doesn’t think so. Asks if the censors have taken anything out of his letters. He censors his men's mail and thinks that mail censorship is a good thing.
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (May 14, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Has been to Missouri, Texas, Georgia, Louisiana, Virginia • Sent Willie a shilling with King George VI & King George V on it [shilling not in envelope]
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (June 11, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Asked again if any of the letters have "been cut up" [censored] and told them they went through the Panama Canal
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (June 25, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • The ranch is the best thing the family has • There isn’t much to do there except go to church four times a week • Sent his Pacific Service Ribbon [not in the archive]
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 2, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Joked around with Dave saying not to burn the tractor
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 7, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • [there are two letters dated July 7, 1944] Sent more pictures home • Had the opportunity to visit Panama city & went through the Panama canal
  - V-mail to Dave from Henry (July 9, 1944 & unknown) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Told Dave to write better & use a dictionary • Asked if Emma and Anne received a bracelet he sent • Connie is on the New Britain Island • He is in New Guinea – island right above Australia
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 21, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Saw some Hindus. They eat a lot different: don’t use spoons or forks, they eat with their fingers. Their main dish is rice. They uses cups and plates; sometimes four men eat out of a large plate
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 24, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Continue seeing a lot of dead Japanese • Told them to put the initials F.LM. so the mail will come faster
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 28, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Moved to another location • Weather—warm & cool ocean breeze • Asked for a book & razor • Willie will soon see that war is not a picnic
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 8, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Advised parents not worry too much about Willie
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 14, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Henry’s birthday • Had church services under a bush shack "that the natives made for a chapel." His Colonel thinks highly of his men and says they are doing a great job in the field. • Sent an Australian shilling worth 16cents [shilling not in letter] • Sent a Japanese coin—worth unknown [coin not in letter]
  - V-mail to Dave from Henry (August 14, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Asked how Dave and Emma getting along • Told Dave to get along with their mom
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 18, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Receives letters regularly from Kay, John, & others • Sent money home $80 ($50 to save & $30 for birthday present) [money not in envelope] • Says that he knows it’s hard to see Willie go, but he will take orders
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 27, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • All of their old friends are passing away & more by the time they come back home • Connie is coming home in September. Hopes the family stays together after the war • Sent home pictures—funny ones: one of the officers got a native grass skirt from a "native" and they had fun taking pictures wearing it. He is living on a coconut plantation right on the beach and their "tent chapel" is only a 100 yards away.
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (August 31, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Dave is home & is thinking about joining the service • Henry asked why Emma hasn’t wrote • Asked if dad developed pictures & told them to send some • Told Dave that the best place for him is on the ranch & not in the service • Told Dave that dad is getting old & if all the boys leave for the service they will lose the ranch & the ranch means a lot to them • Says that Dave is still young & doesn’t understand • Says that the Army is not easy. They have to work hard. Only sleep about four hours • Says that Dave has a vacation on the ranch • Pete said that he went through hell when he was in North Africa, & he could have very easily been killed • Willie was crazy because he disobeyed dad & went to the service –said that he should feel ashamed • Tells Dave to get along with mom because he’s young & doesn’t understand how she feels • Makes it clear that the letters Henry & the boys write to Dad intentionally make the Army sound like a picnic. However he does that so they won’t worry. He’s not lying, he does name a few good things, but if he tells him the truth about what they going through he will start sweating. The boys will tell him how they are going through hell & they all can’t wait to go home
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 2, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Sent $35 to save for him [money not in letter] • Mentioned that the razor was no hurry, but he didn’t make that clear in his letter • Talked about how the letters take a while to get in especially when changing location
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 11, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Sent pictures home, asked about the crops, & gave them an update
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 25, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • He’s in one of the Netherland East Indies Islands • Weather—warm during the day, cool at night • Asks about the crops
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 1, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Asks about the raisins & how it turned out • Have had a few air raids and bombing • A fellow & him spent a week building a bomb shelter
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 6, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • John & Henry are on the same island • They will see each other that day • Asked about the crops
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 15, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Asked if the rain affected the crops • Saw John again the day before • Doesn’t want anything for Christmas except letters & film • Tries to get a picture of John & him but hard to at night • Scott is on German soil
  - V-mail to Dave from Henry (October 16, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Say John the week before • Asks for the new address of John, Scott, & Willie • Asked why Emma doesn’t write—he likes writing to girls [joke]
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 28, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Busy building jungle homes for themselves • Hasn’t seen John for 10 days because they moved and now they are six miles apart
  - V-mail to Dave from Henry (October 29, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • There was many clippings of Connie in the Fresno Bee [newspaper] • Asks about the ranch
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 7, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Days are short because don’t have any lights a night • Hadn’t seen Johnny in three weeks
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 13, 1944, Location-N.E. Indies) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Said there’s nothing to do but to keep busy; Helped clean sea salt fish (& eat them); Weather—Rainy; Some soldiers have chickens so they watch for eggs to eat—rare to eat
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 20, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Got to see John again. • Kay sent John a package with soups & he gave Henry some • Reminded them to get watch from getting repaired • Keep asking about raisins on the farm • Sent a native piece of kitchenware
  - V-mail to Dave from Henry (November 24, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Saw Johnny a few days ago • Asked for more film
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 3, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • There isn’t much to do besides the daily chores, write letters, & read • Weather—hot, Fresno July weather • Sent a check so they can buy Christmas presents for Kay, Emma, Dave, mom & dad • Has another gift for Anne • Caught enough fish to feed 200 men by using TNT or dynamite to stun the fish • Will see John again next week • Wants camera film
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 10, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Saw John the day before • Razor & pocket book arrived • There’s a Jewish officer that is teaching him how to "talk Jewish" [speak Hebrew] • Moved closer to John • Hopes that Dave doesn’t have to join the Army
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 17, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • [A Merry Christmas/ Happy New Year Card is enclosed] • Henry seen John three times and saw Walt Berg from Cross Church
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 25, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Its Christmas day & he had just came from the evening service • Held a Carol Song Service • Worst season for hearing Christmas carols—says that Southern people just don’t care for those things. "They are really different people than we are"
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (January 3, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Weather—very hot in the day & nights nice & cool • Saw John again & John was promoted to Staff Sergeant • Willie got a furlough
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (January 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Found out that Dave will be leaving soon for the service • Wants him to keep this letter with his belongings to help him through the changes that lie ahead • Wants to tell him the “Do’s and Don’ts” about life in the service: 1. Forget about being afraid of things that you don’t know about 2. Do the best that you possibly can 3. Try to overcome his shyness and not be so timid 4. Get along with the boys, especially with all the corporals, sergeants & officers (salute them at all times) 5. Try to be interested in everything they tell you about the army 6. Study & Learn fast 7. Don’t volunteer for everything 8. Don’t listen too much to rumors (part of the time they are not true) 9. Stay away from gambling & drinking unless its beer in the PX Stores 10. Learn to quit drinking when he drinks a beer 11. Stay away from the men that are getting in trouble because they’ll get you in trouble too 12. Go to church as often as you can 13. Write to Dad at least once a week & to Kay, John, Henry, Anne 14. If you need anything from home tell dad or Anne
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (January 21, 1945; Location—N.E. Indies) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Saw John & he said to not worry about him
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (January 28, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • John left the island & sent parents the his new address • Said that work on the ranch will be easier with the tractor
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (February 4, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Sends a bunch of pictures to save • Not working so much—usually doing daily chores, read, play sports, swimming, writing letters • Thinks he’s gaining weight • Has been eating well—ate chicken, beef, steak
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (February 11, 1945, Location—N.E. Indies) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • It is rainy & windy – so much that they even had to brace the tents so it wouldn’t fly away
  - Letter to folks from Henry (February 17, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Talks about how long it takes to receive mail & if speed is necessary to use air mail • He knows where John is located: he's on the same island but can’t tell them anything more than John is safe • Heard from Connie—his current duites are not working him very hard & is safe • Asks if Dave is still at home or has he left for the service yet • Asked about how their home looks and how the crops are • Weather—rained for 3 days. They are "getting meat quite regularly now."
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (February 24, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Sent camera films home for them to save for him • He uses the battery light on his radio for light to write letters
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (March 4, 1945, Location—N.E. Indies) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • V-mail is very slow • Sent more pictures [photographs not in envelope]
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (March 12, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • It’s been rainy but the tents are strong enough to keep the rain away • The food is always warm
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (April 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Cautions his Dad about his Dad's efforts to stop Dave from being inducted into the service: "Whatever you do, don't get into trouble doing it. I know you need him bad but there might not be a thing that you can do to get him out. I don't know what Gearhart or Roosevelt think of it when you keep writing to them." • He has "one ribbon, one battle star and nothing else so far." Emma and Mom are helping on the ranch • Air mail is faster than 3cent mail • [Included with the letter is the Easter Worship Service program for April 1, 1945, 155th Infantry]
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (April 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Difficult to write because the brothers change location and takes a while to get address • Their dad was trying to get Dave out and Henry agrees that he can help on the ranch • Tells Dave to write often to the boys and even more often to Dad
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (April 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Received a letter from Dave a few days ago & he’s doing fine. • Went to morning services –have a choir which sing very well
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (April 24, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • John & Henry have been so close in locations • John & Henry are both in the Philippines, about two miles apart
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (May 2, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Henry saw John four times the week before • Weather—pretty warm, mountains aren’t cool • Finally saw a highway but it was just dirt and two narrow lanes • Feels relieved to be away from "the uncivilized people at the other places. These Philippinoes [Filipinos] can talk good English." Remarked on their education and some are well dressed. They are friendly and they are in a part of the island where most people are Christians • Filipinos’ houses are made of straw and poles • Sent 50 cents home for them to save for him—sent a “peca” = 50cents [peca not in letter]
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (May 3, 1945; Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • John is on the same island as Henry • Henry reports he was not scared when tanks went over him because "they are just real experiences" • Told Dave to get into an anti-tank company rather than a rifle outfits because they don’t walk as much • Reminded Dave to write location and date on each letter • Henry has been overseas for over 15 months now – landed in New Guinea then Ora Bay, Buna, Santa Anna Trail (had a big fight there), then Maffin Bay, Wakde island, • Went to another island that he’s not allowed to mention—all the natives were uncivilized, dirty & half naked. The women wore skirts from the waist down & men wore patches • Sent him a peca [peca not in letter]
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (May 8, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Asked how Dave liked the Army and if he gets homesick once in a while • Church helps a lot –especially if he comes overseas • If the church as a choir—join • Filipinos are glad that they are there—the Japanese swiped everything they had, including clothes. Getting assistance fighting the Japanese from the Filipino guerrillas • First time they met natives that speak English • Talked about President Truman being on the radio
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (May 19, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Henry moved location, but the new location looks like the best he’s seen since he went overseas. • There are rolling hills all over & not many jungles
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (May 26, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Hasn’t had much time to write due to moving so often • Sends films home to keep for him • Talks about ranch—the grapes must be big
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (May 28, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • Willie is on the same island as Henry & John but missed him • Missed Willie because he did not write often enough and so they missed two chances to see him. • Sent Anne a necklace and shell bracelet for Emma • John’s birthday May 28; Emma’s birthday May 18 • Asked Dave what he was planning to do with the money he was saving at home. Told him to ask his officer about the Solider's Deposit which pays 4%, which is more than a savings account • Anne reported that Dave doesn’t get homesick and Henry is glad to hear it. Henry also heard that Fred Priez is now in the service
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (June 3, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • He’s staying at a native shack made of straw and bamboo • John and him were on an island called Morotai—in N.E Indies
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (June 25, 1945, Location of Henry—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    • John is near Henry • Willie was on the same island as Henry but a different part of the island • Talked about seeing lots of nice countries. He saw a waterfall which started dropping from a hill about 600ft. • Five men went home on the point system • Weather—it’s warm, rains every evening, & light breeze during the day • Asked if he’s writing regularly to Dad & Kay [sister]
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (July 4, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Took 20 days to receive Dave’s letter • Henry met with John a week ago • Henry has met a lot of guerilla officers, had dinner with them & lived with them too. Met one officer who was in "that death march" • The markets there are similar to the vegetable markets back at home • Women there all dress like the ones at home
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Sent pictures home [photographs are not in envelope] • Explains that they haven’t heard from John because he’s been moving a lot
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (July 23, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Had two Filipinos kill a small pig & roast him over a fire • Asks if Dave can write longer letters
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (August 4, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    • Give each other updates about the brothers & Henry gets frustrated about the brothers not writing a lot in the letters • Dad birthday - Aug 13, has Kay buy dad a present from Henry
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 8, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Sends negatives and pictures to be saved [letter did not include negatives nor pictures]
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • They heard of Japan’s surrender (after hearing false rumors 3 times) • Hasn’t been able to see John because they are some distance apart • Advises them not to send him any Christmas packages unless it is films • Packages take three months or more to get here & doesn’t know if they’ll change location by then • The dangerous period is over for them – he returned without a scratch from the enemy
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (August 23, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Received Scott’s address last week—has a big stack of mail & was trying to respond asap • Connie doesn’t write much – once every 4 months • Willie wrote him & is doing fine • If Dave has to come overseas it won’t be too bad because it will be guard duty
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (August 27, 1945--Location--Mindanao, Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Willie's letter said he had left the hospital after he had malaria; Henry says that malaria is not dangerous and that some of the men get it, but they are never very sick; All men are now doing guard duty; A bunch of officers were invited to dinner at the guerilla headquarters by the guerilla division commander
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 8, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Asked if Emma can drive the tractor yet • Weather—raining
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (September 14, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Talk about brothers & what position they were in • Connie had about 100 points if not over that • Henry hopes to be home within 6 months—has 86points • Dave is tired of being in the South • Henry has paid Kay to buy all presents for the family & has his folks buy presents for her in the same way • Henry had Kay buy a birthday present for his dad • Asked if Dave is going to get a furlough